Guide to the Donald E. Stanford Papers, 1933-1985 M0466
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Donald E. Stanford Papers
1933-1985
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford, Donald E. (Donald Elwin)
M0466
1.5 Linear Feet
3 boxes
Biographical Note
Donald Elwin Stanford was born in Amherst, Massachusetts on February 7th, 1913. He s obtained both his BA and Phd from Stanford and his MA from Harvard all in English. Before embarking on his teaching career, Stanford was a free-lance writer, and a member of the literary group known as the `Winters circle', centered around Yvor Winters himself. Winters helped the aspiring poets and writers learn more about the art of creative writing, mainly through criticism of one anothers work.
In 1949 Stanford was appointed Instructor to the Alumni Professor of English at Louisiana State University and was promoted to Professor of English in 1953 and then Alumni Professor Emeritus in 1979. He married Maryanna Peterson in 1953 and became the editor of the [unk] Review in 1963. In his capacity as editor of the Review Stanford communicated with those writers and poets who had been an important part of his early writing career: Yvor Winters, Janet Lewis, Elisabeth Bishop, J.V. Cunningham, Allen Tate and Ann Stanford, to name a few.
Throughout his career Stanford received several accolades. He was awarded a Guggenheim fellowship in 1959, Distinguished Faculty Fellowship in 1973 and Distinguished Research Master in 1982 He retired as Professor of English and editor of the Southern Review in 1983.
Among his published works are: New England Earth (poems) 1941; The Traveler (poems) 1955; The Poems of Edward Taylor 1960; Edward Taylor 1965; Nine Essays in Modern Literature 1965; The Selected Poems of Robert Bridges 1974; The Selected Poems of S. Foster Damon 1974; Revolution and Convention in Modern Poetry 1983; In the Classic Mode: The Achievement of Robert Bridges (2 vols.) 1983, 84; John Masefield: Letters to Margaret Bridges 1984, John Masefield Selected Poems 1984; The Cartesian Lawnmower and Other Poems 1984.
Stanford also contributed to journals such as the Southern Review, Hudson Review, [unk] Review, Michigan Quarterly Review, Hopkins Quarterly, etc.
DONALD FLWIN STANFORD
Missing Title
1913 Born, February 7th, Amherst, Massachusetts.
1933 B.A. Stanford University.
1934 M.A. Harvard University.
1949 Instructor to Alumni Professor of English, Louisiana State University.
1953 Phd. Stanford University.
1953 Professor of English, Louisiana State University.
1953 Married Maryanna Peterson, August 14th, Reno, Nevada.
1959 Guggenheim Fellowship.
1961-2 Visiting Professor, Duke University, North Carolina.
1963 Editor of the Southern Review, Louisiana State University.
1973 Distinguished Faculty Fellowship.
1979 Alumni Professor Emeritus, Louisiana State University.
1982 Distinguished Research Master.
1983 Retires as Professor of English and Editor of the Southern Review, Louisiana State University.
1984 Visiting Professor, Texas, A & M University, College Station.
Publications include
1941 New England Earth (poems).
1955 The Traveler, (poems).
1960 The Poems of Edward Taylor.
1965 Edward Taylor.
1965 Nine Essays In Modern Literature.
1974 The Selected Poems of Robert Bridges.
1974 The Selected Poems of S. Foster Damon.
1983 Revolution and Convention in Modern Poetry.
1983 Editor, Dictionary of Literary Biography, vols. 19 & 20.
1983, 84 In the Classic Mode, The Achievement of Robert Bridges. (2 vols.)
1984 John Masefield: Letters to Margaret Bridges.
1984 John Masefield: Selected Poems.
1984 The Cartesian Lawnmower and Other Poems.
Contributed to: Southern Review, Hodson Review, Sewanee Review, Michigan Quarterly Review, Hopkins Quarterly, etc.
Memberships: Phi Beta Kappa, Phi Kappa Phi, PEN, MLA, SAMLA, SCM.
Scope and Content
The collection covers contains copies of correspondence, typescript poems, drafts of books, news clippings and a few photographs.
Correspondence makes up the bulk of the collection covering fifty-two years with as many correspondents, most of whom are important twentieth century literary figures. The collection includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence and in many cases the letters follow chronologically for a considerable time span, providing the reader with a clear, fully documented picture of a certain period. The correspondence provides important biographical information about Donald Stanford as well as valuable insights into the lives of the correspondents.
The subject matter stems primarily from Stanford's position as editor of the Southern Review. Letters contain discussions of articles that are to be submitted and often enclosures of poems. In 1959 all correspondence is concerned with a volume of poetry to be produced for Yvor Winters' sixtieth birthday, which was never published. Many letters also discuss books that Stanford and his correspondents are writing, providing an additional source of information about published pieces by these authors.
The papers from the early period, 1933-49 provide insights into Stanford's early life as a poet and provide information about the `Winters circle'. The collection of letters from Yvor, five folders in all, portrays in detail the highs and lows of Stanford's early career. Through Winters we learn that Stanford as a young, aspiring poet has a poor view of the teaching profession, a profession in which he was to excel. Winters encouraged Stanford to become a teacher, at least to have a job other than as a writer, and his view of those who write alone is in this letter written in September 1933: "There is [nothing] more pathetic and in a way contemptible than the free-lance writer who [attempts] to live by writing and actually lives by borrowing from his more provident friends."
The collection of Donald Stanford gives an important overview of the lives of many important twentieth century literary figures.
All material in this collection is photocopied. Originals reside at Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge (http://lib.lsu.edu/special).
Provenance
Gift of Donald E. Stanford, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use.
Stanford, Donald E. (Donald Elwin)
- Baker, Howard, 1937-1982; 27 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  including 1 newsclipping, 1 photo
- Barth, R.L., 1981-1985; 22 leaves (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bishop, Elisabeth, 1933-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  includes 3 poems, 1 photo
- Bishop, Elisabeth (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bishop, Elisabeth (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Blackmur, 1933-1963; 6 leaves (Box 1, Folder 6)
  includes 1 poem
- Bocock, Maclin, 1976-1982; 11 leaves (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bowers, Edgar, 1958-1980; 44 leaves (Box 1, Folder 8)
  includes 1 poem, 1 letter from Peter Scupham, Sept. 1980
- Bowers, Edgar (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Brooks, Cleanth, 1970-1981; 24 leaves (Box 1, Folder 10)
  includes 1 pamphlet
- Campbell, Kathleen, 1974; 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cassity, Turner, 1959-1980; 10 leaves (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Clark, Eleanor, 1972-1977; 12 leaves (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cowley, Malcom, 1971-1984; 38 leaves (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Cowley, Malcom (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Cunningham, J,V,m, 1933-1982; 43 leaves (Box 1, Folder 16)
  includes 1 poem, 1 newsclippings
- Cunningham, J,V,m (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Daryush, 1970-1977; 52 leaves (Box 1, Folder 18)
  includes 1 poem, list of works
- Daryush (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Davie, Donald, 1960-1984; 38 leaves (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Davie, Donald (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Davis, Catherine, 1959-1972; 17 leaves (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Davis, Dick, 1979-1984; 9 leaves (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Fields, Kenneth, 1966-1980; 17 leaves (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Fitzgerald, Robert, 1940-1974; 6 leaves (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Fraser, John, 1969-1985; 209 leaves (Box 1, Folder 26)
  includes 1 newsclipping, drafts for anthology
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Fraser, John (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Fuller, Roy, 1972-1985; 99 leaves (Box 1, Folder 36)
  includes 1 newsclipping
- Fuller, Roy (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Fuller, Roy (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Fuller, Roy (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Fuller, Roy (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Gibbs, Barbara, 1933-1972; 13 leaves (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Gordon, Caroline, 1964-1977; 58 leaves (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Gordon, Caroline (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Gordon, Caroline (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Guerard, Albert, 1934-1985; 55 leaves (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Guerard, Albert (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Gullans, Chalres, 1959-1983; 9 leaves (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Gunn, Thom, 1959-1981; 8 leaves (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Hayes, Ann, 1972-1963 ***********; 18 leaves (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Holt, Achilles (Tex), 1934-1936; 16 leaves (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Josephson, 1969-1977; 69 leaves (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Josephson (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Josephson (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Lavin, Mary, 1970-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Lewis, Janet, 1933-1985; 138 leaves (Box 2, Folder 15)
  includes 17 poems, 1 newsclipping
- Lewis, Janet (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Lewis, Janet (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Lewis, Janet (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Lewis, Janet (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Lewis, Janet (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Lewis, Janet (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Middlebrook, Diane, 1972-1980; 5 leaves (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Moore, Marianne, 1925-1959; 10 leaves (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Oates, Joyce Carol, 1971-1981; 26 leaves (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Oliver, Raymond, 1971-1984; 43 leaves (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Oliver, Raymond (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Peterson, Douglas, 1969-1982; 19 leaves (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Peterson, Margaret (Jan), 1959-1984; 26 leaves (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Pinkerton, Helen, 1970-1983; 30 leaves (Box 2, Folder 29)
  includes 2 poems
- Pinkerton, Helen (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Pitter, Ruth, 1972-1976; 5 leaves (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Powell, Grosvener, 1975-1985; 37 leaves (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Powell, Grosvener (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Raine, Kathleen, 1971-1985; 19 leaves (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Ramsey, Henry, 1959-1984; 8 leaves (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Saroyan, William, 1968-1969; 5 leaves (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Sherry, Pearl Andelson, 1970-1981; 7 leaves (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Spencer, Theodore, 1935-1936; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Stafford, Clayton, 1954-1975; 8 leaves (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Stanford, Ann, 1936-1984; 75 leaves (Box 3, Folder 1)
  includes 2 poems, 1 newsclipping
- Stanford, Ann (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Stanford, Ann (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Stanford, Ann (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Steele, Timothy, 1971-1985; 23 leaves (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Tate, Allen, 1939-1978; 71 leaves (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Tate, Allen (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Tate, Allen (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Tate, Allen (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Trimpi, Wesley, 1959-1981; 11 leaves (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Voegelin, Eric, 1969-1981; 33 leaves (Box 3, Folder 11)
  includes 1 photograph
- Voegelin, Eric (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Warren, Robert Penn, 1963-1981; 71 leaves (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Warren, Robert Penn (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Warren, Robert Penn (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Warren, Robert Penn (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Wilmer, Clive, 1978-1984; 19 leaves (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Winters, Yvor, 1933-1967; 100 leaves (Box 3, Folder 18)
  includes 20 poems
- Winters, Yvor (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Winters, Yvor (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Winters, Yvor (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Winters, Yvor (Box 3, Folder 22)